A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director of Program Planning and Development FA222
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director of Program Planning and Development
1970-1986
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA222
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
In April 1970, as a special assistant to the President, Rodney W. Nichols was appointed Director of Program Planning and Development. The program was created to develop directions of future programs of research and education and to assist in finding resources to fulfill those programs. In November 1971 Ray F. Carmichael was appointed as Director of Development at The University to assist the Board of Trustees Development Committee, chaired by C.W. Cook and to work with Mr. Nichols in long range planning.
In 1972 at a meeting on October 31 the University Trustees elected Rodney W. Nichols to the new post of vice-president for program planning and development.
In November 1973 Dr. Seitz announced two newly created positions. Robert L. Van Valer was named Director of Trust and Estate Gift plans, and George Smith was appointed assistant director for development.
September 19, 1974, Bruce L. Crisman was appointed Development Officer at The Rockefeller University. Mr. Crisman resigned April 1975 and was replaced in September by Barry W. Dress, formerly development administrator at Pace University.
January 25, 1977 announcement was made that David O. Smith was appointed to the Development Office, as director, capital resources. His initial responsibilities will be in the area of corporate funding.
In,1977 Mary Detwiler Smith was named coordinator of Development services with responsibility for donor relations and to assist in developing contacts with prospective donors among general welfare, personal and family foundations.
January 1978 Patrick J. Garvey was appointed director of corporate and foundation relations to replace David O. Smith who resigned.
Early in 1979 Ray F. Carmichael left the University to accept a post at the Sidney Farber Cancer Center in Boston.
In August 1979 Frederick G. Lehmann was appointed as Executive Director for Development and Public Affairs.
In July 1985 Barry Dress was appointed Vice President for University Relations (new post). Judith N. Schwartz was appointed Director of Public Information, succeeding Mr. Fulvio Bardossi who has retired. Mr. Marc S. Kaplan was appointed Public Information Officer. (See news release, 18 July 1985)
Scope and Contents note
Pamphlet prepared for use in fund raising.
News releases regarding appointment.
News releases regarding grants toward $118 million development effort.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 360
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Other Finding Aids
For related material see:
FA1021 Rockefeller University records, Development Office, Publications
Arrangement
As received.
Philanthropy -- United States; Philanthropy; Medical sciences; Medical research; Biology -- Research
- News releases, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings, (photocopies and originals) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photos (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Brochures (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Gift Opportunities" Office of the President, 1971 June; Brochure
  - "About The Rockefeller University", circa 1976; Brochure
  - "To Fulfill the Promise" August 1971, Office of the President, 1971 August; Brochure
  - "New Initiatives in Biological and Medical Research", 1983 March; Brochure
  - "The Promise of the Future" [Frederick Seitz, President], 2 bound volumes
- Development Report, Spring 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Cancer Research at The Rockefeller University" Prepared by the Development Office, 1983-1984; Brochure (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Essentials for Discovery (New York City: The Rockefeller University, 1984), Booklet, illustrated. 32 pp. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Establishment of Toyotoa Professorship, 1986 January; 2.5" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Barry Dress memorandum, 7 Jan 1986; copy of Japanese "catalog" with translation, traditional celebration of occasion.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Received 10 January 1986 from Barry Dress via S.W. Mirsky.
- Brochures, 3 copies of each
  Received from Barry Dress via Sonya W. Mirsky, 22 January 1987.
  - "The Rockefeller University Associates Program: A Special Purpose", 1983 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Rockefeller University Associates: Partners in Discovery", 1985 December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "The Rockefeller University Associates", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)